What I want you to try to do is you're going to go
ahead and take that user's page that you were working on again.
This time, see what you can do on that component to
actually use the setup function to
refactor at the bare minimum the fetch data.
Then if you have the time,
if you're free to go ahead and practice using the ref,
reactive, computed, or whatever you prefer.
All right. How did that feel for everyone?
I know that we did some pairing here in the room,
but people online can let me know how that experience went.
If you have questions, in the meantime,
I'm going to go ahead and start walking through
the solution to see how I would approach this.
Okay. So let's go ahead and dive into the code.
As we can see here, what we want to do is we want to
migrate the stuff we've been doing,
especially as far as the fetch stuff into our setup function.
So let's go ahead and start doing that.
First thing first, again,
I always like to put my setup before data as a reminder to
myself that this is not going to
actually be able to access anything below it.
It can go top down,
but there's nothing going bottom up.
So let's do a couple of things.
Let's see. All right.
So this method here, async functions,
let's start actually by moving the data.
The data here, I'm going to go ahead and use the reactive,
since that's something that at least feels a little bit more
familiar to people.
I think when they're first getting started with Composition API.
So we'll import reactive from view,
and we'll create that state,
which is going to be a reactive object.
Inside of there, I'm going to have this thing called
UserList and UserList will then be this array.
So this allows me to then get rid of this data property.
The only thing we need to do now is actually return the state here,
and then to show that this works,
what we can do is you can say this.state.userList,
and then if everything should still work,
the only thing we need to change is here,
state.userList, and we save that.
Let's go and see. If we refresh up,
it's down because why,
because there's no local dev running.
Okay. There we go.
You can see everything's still working.
All right. So refactored, step one, good to go.
Next thing we need to do,
the main thing we want to do is dysfunction of methods.
So some of you caught on because you might be thinking,
wait, is there a methods thing that I need to import from view?
The answer is no,
because one way we introduced methods earlier.
Remember what I said?
Methods are really just JavaScript functions that view has access to.
So in other words,
there's nothing special about them because they're JavaScript functions.
So we can do, if we can take this,
and we can copy this here,
and basically say this is an async function called fetch users.
Now, before we move on though,
there's a couple things that's going to break.
One, we know for a fact that this does not work anymore,
because why we're not in options API,
we're in composition API.
So we have this state here that's deleted,
and then this is currently state.userList,
we equal that, and we have the async here.
So what we need to do is let's go ahead and also do,
we also don't have, or actually wait,
there's the function there, that's fine,
and then let's go and start by returning it.
We'll slowly refactor this so we can see it step by step,
piece by piece.
Bum bum bum bum, there it's that.
Now we save this though,
you'll notice everything seems to still be working,
and so we'll see that hello hello.
And so here's the thing though,
is that right now fetch users has a very implicit tie
to our state right now.
In other words, if we wanted to fetch users in another context,
we would then need to create another function theoretically,
but this is JavaScript, this is programming,
we don't want that,
that's something that wouldn't make a lot of sense.
And so what you probably want to do
is actually separate the state assignment here
from the function itself.
So in other words, what we'd like to do
is actually say state.userList out here
is equal to what happens when we've run fetch users.
That's actually what we'd like to do.
And so what we'd really want
is to basically kind of return the response
that comes from this.
So when you're looking at this
and you're looking at the return,
you might think, okay, I'm just gonna return the promise.
Now, apparently when it comes to returning promises
inside of you, it gets a little bit tricky
because then you have to manage
like resolving the promise and that kind of stuff.
And so at least for me, what I tried to do actually
is I will actually just create the response
that's being awaited.
So basically this cons response.
And what I do is return the response directly.
And that's what's being returned
rather than returning the entire promise itself.
And that's what should allow this thing
to assign itself to this.
But before we finish though,
remember that fetch users is an async function,
which means what?
We need to await keyword here.
And if we need to await keyword here, what does that mean?
We also need the async key
all the way up here inside of setup.
And then we save that,
we get our predictable yelling at us message.
And the reason for that is because why?
Because the parent is like, whoa, whoa, whoa,
you have this thing that's doing async function,
it might be broken.
Give me something to fall back on.
So let's go and fix that.
If you go inside of app.view inside of setup view,
we have this component here.
And so what we're gonna do is we're gonna wrap it
in a suspense component.
And then we'll have our template with the vslot of fallback.
And then what we'll do here is then go data is loading, save.
And if you actually saw the small blink,
it actually does do the data is loading
because view actually is waiting for something.
So granted, again, for your production level apps,
you probably will want some sort of nice loading page
and whatnot for that.
But for now we're just doing that with simple text.
But now if we take a look,
it looks like everything is working as expected.
Now the thing is though,
we're actually doing a double call here if you realize it
in that we're returning the fetch users method,
but it's actually already being called
inside of your setup method.
So really, we don't even need this here.
So we can actually delete our entire created lifecycle hook.
And what you have now here is basically your entire user page
using the composition API within the options API.
And everything is working as expected.
Thankfully.